Guide to the John Fee Embree Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
John Fee Embree papers
1926-1950
1945-1950
MS 976
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2
(4 boxes)
Miscellaneous papers of John Fee Embree, sociologist and director of Southeast Asia Studies at Yale University, 1950. Two journals of trips to the Far East, 1926 and 1947-1948, the latter accompanied by numerous photographs, postcards, wood cuts, and other illustrations are included. Also in the papers are correspondence and mimeographed memoranda of the American Council of Learned Societies, the Social Science Research Council and the Far Eastern Association, 1948-1951, on the advancement of Asian studies in the United States. There are also documents, reports and lecture outlines from the School of Naval Administration, Hoover Institute, 1945-1946, on the Far East and countries in the South Pacific, and manuscripts by Embree on East Asia and the Japanese in America.
Embree, John F. (John Fee), 1908-1950
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Part of the John F. Embree Papers were given to Yale University Library by Mrs. Ella L. Wiswell in 1965 and by Stanford University in 1968.
Scope and Contents
The John F. Embree Papers consist of journals, manuscripts, photographs, woodcuts, reprints, and miscellaneous papers spanning from 1926 to 1950. Most are related to Embree's education and employment as a scholar in Asian studies. Researchers will find additional material in the Edwin Rogers Embree Papers, Manuscript Group No. 198.
Part of the John F. Embree Papers were given to Yale University Library by Mrs. Ella L. Wiswell in 1965 and by Stanford University in 1968. The rest appear to have been transferred from his father's papers.
Biographical / Historical
John Fee Embree, 1908-1950: sociologist and anthropologist; B.A., University of Hawaii, 1931; M.A., University of Toronto, 1934; Ph.D., University of Chicago, 1937; associate professor, sociology, Yale University, 1948-1950; research associate, anthropology and director, Southeast Asia Studies, Yale University, 1950.
Historical Register of Yale University, 1937-1951.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Asia -- Description and travel; Southeast Asia -- Description and travel; Anthropologists; Sociologists; Embree, John F. (John Fee), 1908-1950; American Council of Learned Societies; Association for Asian Studies; Social Science Research Council (U.S.); Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University -- Officals and employees; Yale University. Southeast Asia Studies
- Inventory
  - "Family journal," February 3, 1926 to July 17, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    This is a report of a trip beginning with Embree's arrival in Kobe, with entries for Tokyo, Nara, Kyoto via Toba and Yamada, Singapore, Batavia, Siam, Penang, Colombo, Ceylon, Suez, Marseilles, Paris.
  - Journal, v. 1, Mar 26, 1927 to Jan 18, 1948. p.22-255 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    I. Travel notes on Hong Kong, Manila, Batavia and Singapore. Mar 26-Apr 8, 1947
    II. Bangkok. Early impressions. Apr 10-20, 1947
    III. Bangkok. Apr 20-30, 1947.
    IV. Bangkok. May 3-Jul 30, 1947
    V. Chiengmai. Jul 3l-Aug 5, 1947
    VII. (sic) Saigon. Aug-Oct 1947
    [unnumbered]. Hanoi. Nov 2-Jan 18,1948
  - Journal, v.2, Jan 20, 1948-April 23, 1948. p.256-422 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    VIII. Laos. Jan 20-Feb 4, 1948
    IX. Cambodia. Feb 8-Feb 20, 1948
    X. Burma. Feb 20-Mar 7, 1948
    [XI] Indonesia. Mar 8-Mar 26, 1948
    VI. [?] Siam Summary [Misplaced. Should be in v.1]
    [unnumbered] Saigon. Mar 31-Apr 23, 1948
  - Journals (Supplement). Figs. 1-87 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    [Photographs of places and persons mentioned in the journals in folders 2 and 3]
  - Journals (Supplement). Figs. 88-183 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    [Photographs of persons and places mentioned in the journals in folders 2 and
    3]
  - Photographs, postcards, wood-cuts, magazine illustrations and other pictures, arranged by country. Photographs and other materials made or collected presumably in 1947-1948. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Burma (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Cambodia Photographs, postcards (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Cambodia. Woodcuts Story of Indra. Nos. 11-20. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    See also box 2, folder 11
  - Indonesia (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Laos. Photographs, postcards (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Laos. Woodcuts. Nos. 1-30. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    See box 2, folder 8
  - Philippines. Photographs (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Thailand. Photographs (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Vietnam. Photographs (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Hoover Institute. School of Naval Administration Documents 1 - 25. 1946. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - ________. Documents 26 - 65. 1946 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - ________. Documents 66 - 97. 1946 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - ________. Documents 98 - 108. 1946 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - [The documents in folders. 15-18 are a series of reports-ethnographic, economic, sociological, historical, etc.-on countries in the Far East and in the South Pacific.] (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Papers relating to the Far Eastern Association, 1948-1950 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - ACLS - SSRC Joint Committee on Southern Asia. Papers, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - [underline].Papers, 1950-1951 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Maspero, Georges. The Kingdom of Champa. A translation of Chapter I of Le Royaume du Champa [by John Fee Embree]. Yale University, Southeast Asia Studies, 1949. 56 leaves (typescript, mimeographed). (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous manuscripts
    - Two American writers at the present, day. (On Willa Cather and Sinclair Lewis.) 8 p. (typescript), 1927 November 23 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Ascent of Waialeale. A personal narrative. 63 p. (typescript), 1932 March-April (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - On the face of it. Notes on a summer in Karuigawa, Japan 1932. 68 p. (photostatic copy of ms.) Photographs and postcards laid in, 1932 June 10-September 10 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Embree, John and Ella. Preliminary report on the social organization of Suye Mura, Island of Kyushu, Japan 28,iii p. (mimeographed), 1936 February 15 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - KGU Radio Broadcast. On Richard Wright's Native Son. 9 p. (typescript), 1940 May 8 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Some causes of unrest at Relocation Centers, 5 p. (typescript carbon), 1943 January 7 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Americans of Japanese ancestry, 5 p., (mimeographed), [1943?] (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - TL (carbon copy) to Harry D. Gideonse criticizing his speech, "American policy in Indonesia." 6 p., 1949 June 8 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Proposal for a social study of an Asiatic city. As a first step in a comparative urban sociology and an essential base of knowledge for modern international relations without war. 5 p. (typed carbon) With covering letter to Edwin Rogers Embree, 1949 June 28 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Proposal to U.S. government
    - The FEAP and the LEAP* A project for East Asia. 1948 January 29, 5, 16 p. (typescript) charts (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Reprints of articles
    - "Relocation of Japanese in United States," Journal of the Washington Academy of Sciences. v.33, no.8, 1943 August 15 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - "Military occupation of Japan," Far Eastern Survey, 1944 September 20 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - "Democracy in postwar Japan," The American Journal of Sociology, v.1, no. 3, 1944 November (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - "A visit to Laos, French Indochina," Journal of the Washington Academy of Sciences, v. 39, no. 5, 1949 May 15 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - "Some problems of an American cultural officer in Asia," American Anthropologist. v. 51, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 7)